<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon on the Second Commandement preached in Saint Pauls Church, Ianuarie 6. 1623. By Iohn Squire vicar of Saint Leonard in Shorditch by London.</title>
            <author>Squire, John, ca. 1588-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23115</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121755</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856922</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856922</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22564</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12808)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22564)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1293:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon on the Second Commandement preached in Saint Pauls Church, Ianuarie 6. 1623. By Iohn Squire vicar of Saint Leonard in Shorditch by London.</title>
                  <author>Squire, John, ca. 1588-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W[illiam] S[tansby] for Nathanael Newbery, and are to be sold at his shops at the signe of the Starre vnder Saint Peters Church in Cornhill, and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The year of the sermon is given according to Lady Day dating.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ten commandments --  Images --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22564:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON ON THE SECOND COMMANDEMENT: Preached in Saint PAVLS Church, <hi>Januarie</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>1623.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> IOHN SQVIRE <hi>Vicar of Saint</hi> LEONARD <hi>in</hi> Shorditch <hi>by</hi> London.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>W. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhops at the ſigne of the Starre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> and in <hi>Popes-head</hi> Alley.</p>
            <p>1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22564:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22564:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE REVEREND, THEOPHILVS AYLMER, <hi>Doctor of Diuinitie, and Arch-Deacon of London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> May not <hi>rob</hi> you: take your <hi>owne.</hi> Your <hi>owne</hi> is this <hi>Sermon: origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, efficiently, occaſionally,</hi> and <hi>authoritatiuely:</hi> Firſt, you ſent me to the <hi>Vniuerſitie:</hi> there your <hi>cost, counſell,</hi> and <hi>care,</hi> made me a <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Scholer,</hi> and <hi>Fellow.</hi> Secondly, you <hi>call'd</hi> me from the <hi>Vniuerſitie,</hi> to a <hi>Liuing</hi> of your <hi>owne Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> a <hi>Donatiue indeed;</hi> without <hi>Simonie,</hi> or <hi>Flatterie.</hi> Would God euery Engliſh <hi>Patron,</hi> and <hi>Paſtor,</hi> could ſay <hi>ſo much,</hi> and <hi>ſo truly.</hi> Thirdly, Your diſcourſe did direct me to this <hi>Text.</hi> Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, As <hi>your Subſtitute,</hi> I preached theſe <hi>Meditations.</hi> Take therefore <hi>your owne,</hi> this <hi>Sermon:</hi> with <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> alſo. Who <hi>proclaymeth</hi> himſelfe <hi>bankrupt,</hi> that he is able <hi>to pay no more:</hi> you hauing bound him in a farther <hi>Obligation.</hi> But he hopeth, <hi>you will accept him,</hi> as you hope <hi>God will accept you,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 12. And ſo much he promiſeth <hi>to you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,</hi> euer to reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, in Christ to be vſed. <hi>IOHN SQVIRE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22564:3"/>
            <head>To the moderate <hi>Romiſh</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, <hi>and the vnſetled</hi> Engliſh <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> Knowledge, Zeale, <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon, doth not indeauour to</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>on you</hi> Faith implicit; <hi>from the authoritie of a</hi> Mother, <hi>the</hi> Church; <hi>either of yours</hi> Romiſh, <hi>or of ours</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. <hi>But to</hi> propoſe <hi>to you,</hi> Truth explicit: <hi>from the veritie of a</hi> Father, <hi>euen of our</hi> owne God, <hi>in his</hi> owne Word. <hi>When I leaue it, doe you leaue me: though you be but</hi> Men, <hi>and I could be euen</hi> an Angell. <hi>While I follow it, you ſhould follow</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>me, though you could be</hi> euen Apoſtles, <hi>and I but a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 3.</note> Man, <hi>yee a</hi> Phariſie. <hi>To the end, that this Truth may be thus embraced:</hi> I preach this to you, doe you pray for mee: <hi>and</hi> our common Chriſt bleſſe vs all.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, in the Truth. <hi>IHON SQVIRE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22564:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON THE SECOND COMMANDEMENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EXOD. 20. 4, 5, and 6.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe ten Commandements, containe one thing: the dutie of Man. But that is twofold: Supreme, to his Father, in the firſt; and Subordinate, to his Brother in the ſecond Table. Our Dutie to God, muſt bee both <hi>Internall,</hi> in the firſt Commandement; and <hi>Externall,</hi> in the three following; and that in three reſpects, of <hi>Things,</hi> in the ſecond; of <hi>Words,</hi> in the third; and of <hi>Times,</hi> in the fourth. This Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond then, is a Commandement inioyning Things concerning our externall dutie to God. It is nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue: forbidding <hi>literally,</hi> onely the worſhipping of Images: but <hi>ſynecdochically,</hi> all <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, will-worſhip,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22564:4"/> or deuiſed deuotion. In it is touched the very pith of all all precepts: both the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to which, and the argument by which it doth perſwade vs: <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, nor any likeneſſe of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in the water vnder the earth: Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, nor worſhip them.</hi> This is the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment praefixt; to which is affixt, as commanding an argument: <hi>For, I the Lord thy God, am a iealous God, viſiting the ſinnes of the Fathers vpon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, vnto the third and fourth generation in them that hate me: &amp; ſhewing mercy vnto thouſands of them that loue me, and keepe my commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Commandement forbiddeth all men, two things concerning Images: their Purpoſe, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, nor any likeneſſe, of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in the water vnder the earth:</hi> and their Practice, <hi>thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, nor worſhip them.</hi> And that the Commandement may the better deſcend into our hearts, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth aſcend from two heads. Firſt, hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth vs from his Iuſtneſſe, <hi>for I the Lord thy God am a iealous God, which viſit the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the children, vnto the third, and fourth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in them that hate mee.</hi> Secondly from his Goodneſſe, <hi>and ſhewing mercy vnto thouſands in them that loue me, and keepe my Commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That my diſcourſe may not altogether floate, in this fathomleſſe ſea, I muſt diue a little deeper, by another ſubdiuiſion. To preuent the very Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22564:4"/> of Image-idolatrie, the Lord doth here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe a plaine Prohibition, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image:</hi> and to make that yet plainer, he annexeth a plaine Expoſition, <hi>nor any likeneſſe, of any thing, that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in the water vnder the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, for as much as that Purpoſe is the Parent which giueth life to the Practice: he ſmiteth at the Bodie of Image-adoration, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them:</hi> and at the Soule thereof, <hi>nor Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them.</hi> That he may euen kill Idolatrie, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiteth both the inferiour and ſuperiour act there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: men may neither <hi>bow</hi> to them, nor <hi>worſhip</hi> them.</p>
            <p>And that this may bee (not <hi>brutum fulmen)</hi> a piercing precept, he doth proteſt his Iuſtneſſe, both in regard of the Puniſher, <hi>for I the Lord thy God am a iealous God:</hi> and of the Puniſhment, <hi>viſiting the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the children, vnto the third and fourth generation in them that hate mee.</hi> Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Lord may appeare to be, not onely, a God to affright the bad, by his Iuſtneſſe; but alſo a Father to inuite the good, by his Goodneſſe; hee proclaymeth that alſo in three remarkable particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. Firſt, the Qualitie, it is excellent: <hi>I will ſhew mercy.</hi> Secondly, the Quantitie, it is infinite, <hi>vnto thouſands.</hi> Thirdly, the Qualification, it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; God will put his owne liuerie on his owne ſeruants: ſome men are as it were, marked out for the mercy of their Maker: <hi>I will ſhew mercy on them that loue me and keepe my Commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here wee haue a long Text, but a little Time.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22564:5"/> Therefore, God Almightie enlarge our hearts, that we may receiue much by our little, yet ſerious attention.</p>
            <p>To runne ouer theſe particulars yet more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly: heare the firſt three words, in two words. <hi>Non facies tibi ſculptile: Non facies,</hi> THOV <hi>ſhalt not:</hi> a ſingular note, from this phraſe of the ſingular number. God doth as it were take the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at their word: <hi>chap.</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. all the people ſaid, <hi>All that the Lord hath ſpoken, wee will doe.</hi> Heere God doth tye them to a perſonall performance of that generall promiſe, THOV <hi>ſhalt haue no other gods but me,</hi> and THOV <hi>ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image.</hi> Whereby wee may ſee that <hi>coecum idolum</hi> (as our learned Biſhop of Wincheſter doth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tortura Torti, pag.</hi> 9.</note> terme it) that Blind idoll, implicit Faith.</p>
            <p>Doe not take vp thy Truth on truſt, from the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> from the <hi>Pope,</hi> or from the <hi>Church.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they doe teach thee, this phraſe may aſſure thee, that no <hi>Coliers Faith</hi> can blanch this <hi>Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian crime:</hi> but at that day, God will queſtion thee in this phraſe, <hi>Tu feciſti?</hi> diddeſt <hi>Thou</hi> make any grauen Image?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not make any grauen Image</hi> Tibi, <hi>to thy ſelfe:</hi> take this phraſe <hi>Tibi,</hi> to thy ſelfe alſo, it merits thy attention. It is an Hebraiſme, ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that men muſt make no Images for Religion, of their owne heads, without Gods command. <hi>Moſes</hi> indeed made an Image, the Braſen image, but not <hi>Sibi</hi> to himſelfe: and <hi>Solomon</hi> made Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the Cherubins, but not <hi>Sibi</hi> of his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention. God himſelfe commanded the one, <hi>Num.</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:22564:5"/> 21. 8. and the other, 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 6. 23. But it ſeemeth, the Succeſſour of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> hath a prerogatiue aboue the perſon of <hi>Moſes. Solomon</hi> indeed did not, durſt not make an Image, <hi>Sibi,</hi> to himſelfe, of his owne authoritie: but behold, a greater than <hi>Solomon</hi> is here, the Pope doth make Images <hi>Sibi,</hi> to himſelfe, and commandeth them to be made, by others alſo. But if he will make an Image for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, let him make an anſwer for himſelfe alſo: Be not thou partaker of other mens ſinnes. <hi>Ne facies Tibi:</hi> make no grauen Image to thy ſelfe, till thou canſt finde ſome plaine place of Scripture expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to command it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith <hi>Pagnine,</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Sculpere,</hi> or <hi>Dolare,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Paſal. Peſel.</note> to carue or graue: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sculptile (&amp; dicitur tam de lignis, quàm de lapidibus)</hi> any Image carued in wood, or grauen in ſtone. By the <hi>Septuagints</hi> it is tranſlated, both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an Idoll, as here, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 4. and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an Image, as <hi>Eſay</hi> 40. 18. Which is an hint ſufficient, to anticipate that Idol-diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, betwixt an <hi>Image,</hi> and an <hi>Idol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond point doth inhibite a ſecond ſort of Images, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by the former word ſome vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <note place="margin">Temounah.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Images framed with caruing or gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing tooles: by this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Images formed with a Pen, or Pencill, <hi>Statues</hi> or <hi>Pictures.</hi> Others take this laſt word in a more large ſence, to ſignifie (as our tranſlation doth alſo render it) <hi>any likeneſſe: Similitudo,</hi> be it <hi>figura</hi> or <hi>phantaſma,</hi> ſayth <hi>Pag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oce</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> either the outward action of the hand, or the inward fiction of the minde. <hi>Dij factitij</hi> or <hi>fictitij,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:22564:6"/> as <hi>Caluine</hi> ſpeaketh: be the intention of man what it will, or the inuention of man, what it can: here is a generall interdiction of all Images: <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any likeneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though this be plaine enough, yet is the Lord pleaſed to explaine this Precept, by an enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, nor any likeneſſe of any thing, in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in the water vnder the earth:</hi> that is, no Image muſt be made to religious vſe, of any, either Fowle of the aire, or Starre of the skie; either of Beaſt of the field, or Tree of the forreſt; either of Men on the land, or Fiſh of the ſea: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>nec deſuper, nec deſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bamajim. Baſhamajim.</note> not any likeneſſe, of any thing, in any place. Surely if ſome had not ſet themſelues, to ſupport their opiniatiue concluſion, I could not imagine, how it were poſſible, for any man, to exempt any Image, from this generall diſtribution, by their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſubtile diſtinctions.</p>
            <p>The precept hauing prohibited the purpoſe, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth to the Practice: <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, nor worſhip them.</hi> The firſt word, <hi>to bow,</hi> in the Hebrew is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to humble ones ſelf, with the ſignes <note place="margin">Shachah.</note> of humiliation: as baring the head, bending the knee, bowing the bodie, ſpreading the armes, &amp;c. In Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, comming of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Canis,</hi> a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor taken from the manner of Spaniels, when <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanch. in Praec.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>pag.</hi> 367.</note> they couch, and crouch on the ground before their Maſters. Our Latine tranſlation is, <hi>incuruare,</hi> to bow, expreſſing only one geſture, but inuoluing all the other. The Image-aduocates, that they may
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22564:6"/> reſerue a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one ſtarting hole, for an eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, tranſlate it, <hi>non adorabis, thou ſhalt not adore</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>B. Bonner in ſec. Praeceptum. pag.</hi> 249.</note> 
               <hi>them.</hi> Although this make a tautologie, the next word, <hi>coles,</hi> ſignifying <hi>Worſhip,</hi> or <hi>Adoration:</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe wee admit this their owne tranſlation, but with their owne diſtinction. <hi>Adoration</hi> is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, ſayth <hi>Lyra, Signi &amp; Facti,</hi> the outward, of the Action; and the inward, of the Affection: it is here vſed in the firſt ſence, as alſo 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 5. 18. Thus then runneth the inhibition, <hi>Thou ſhalt not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme any religious geſture, to any Image.</hi> Now, whether this bee not the Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when they creepe to a Croſſe, kneele to an Image, and kiſſe them both; Let the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholikes</hi> themſelues gaineſay: but I thinke they cannot gaineſay ſo common a Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</p>
            <p>The ſecond point prohibited in our Practice, is <hi>Worſhip:</hi> the Hebrew terme is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which the <note place="margin">Gnauad.</note> Greekes turne by two words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 10. and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Coloſs.</hi> 3. 24. (where note by the way, that diſtinction of <hi>Dulia</hi> and <hi>Latria,</hi> may be taken out of the way, it is not vncontroulable, its mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are not diſtinct, it ſelfe therefore is no diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) the Latines tranſlate it by one word <hi>Seruire,</hi> to ſerue, it being a metaphore from Seruants. But this Seruice, being (in Religion) of an higher na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, our tranſlators doe well expreſſe it, by a word of an higher name, <hi>Worſhip.</hi> Now this worſhip, or religious ſeruice, conſiſteth of many particulars, all inhibited by the Scriptures, to be exhibited to Pictures: as inuocation of them, <hi>Eſay</hi> 44. 17.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22564:7"/> Thankes to them, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2. 27. no not to Bow before them, 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 25. 14. Preaching for them, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2. 8. Swearing by them <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1. 5. Sacrificing, 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17. 35. Cenſing, <hi>Ier.</hi> 18. 15. &amp;c. The ſence then is this: impart no ſuch ſeruice, to any Image: for thereby thou ſhalt make it an Idoll, 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. 4. and thy ſelfe, an Idolater, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 25. Thus are wee come <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ad vmbelicum vſque,</hi> to the Nauel, middle, and pith of this Commandement.</p>
            <p>From commanding, our God goeth on to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading. The firſt Argument is from his <hi>Iuſtneſſe:</hi> in which the Puniſher is premiſed, as a preface to the Puniſhment, <hi>I the Lord thy God, am a iealous God.</hi> The Lord, <hi>Iehouah,</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to bee.</hi> God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <note place="margin">Haiah.</note> the Beeing, <hi>ens entium,</hi> in himſelfe primitiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in vs deriuatiuely: in him wee haue our Beeing, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 28. <hi>Elohim, God,</hi> contradiſtinct to <hi>Elelim,</hi> the laſt ſignifying <hi>(vanities)</hi> a falſe god: the firſt a true God. The affixe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Thy God.</hi> Thy <note place="margin">Eloheca.</note> God by purchace, and thy God by promiſe: I bought thee, and brought thee from <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the <hi>Egyptian</hi> ſlauerie, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. and Thou diddeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to heare me, and obey mee, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 8. three words, three Arguments.</p>
            <lg n="1">
               <l>1. <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip him alone, who is Iehouah, thy Creator.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But an Image is (a creature) not Iehouah, thy Creator.</hi> Therefore.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not worſhip an Image.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <l>2. <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip him alone, who is Elohim, the true God.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:22564:7"/>
               <l> 
                  <hi>But Images are not</hi> Elohim, <hi>true Gods; but</hi> Elilim, <hi>falſe gods.</hi> Therefore,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Images are not to be worſhipped.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <l>3. <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip none but Thy God, who did purchaſe thee, and whom thou didſt promiſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But an Image is not Thy God, it did not purchaſe thee, thou didſt not promiſe it.</hi> Therefore,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou ſhall not worſhip an Image.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>If a confirmd Idolater could <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, out-face theſe three Arguments, theſe three Titles of God: God doth ſend out Seconds, a ſupply, and doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enforce his perſwaſion, by two other Attributes, <hi>a iealous God.</hi> Two things animate an Adultereſſe to be impudent and incorrigible in her Adulterie: if her huſband be either milde, that he wil not, or if he be awed, that he cannot reuenge that iniurie. God here argueth from the contrarie to theſe two. <hi>I am</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>fortis,</hi> ſtrong; and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">El. Kanna.</note> 
               <hi>Zelotes,</hi> iealous: and thus lieth the Argument.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not prouoke him, who both can and will plague thee, by worſhipping Images.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>But I am a ſtrong iealous God, who both can, and will plague thee.</hi> Therefore,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not worſhip Images.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Finally, God is ſometimes termed the Husband of his people, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2. 2. and Idolatrie, Adulterie, <hi>Ier.</hi> 3. 20. therefore as the iealous man doth rage, and will not ſpare in the day of vengeance. <hi>Prou.</hi> 6. 34. ſo God menaceth from the ſame metaphor. <hi>Thou ſhalt not worſhip any Image: For—I the Lord thy God am a iealous God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:22564:8"/>
            <p> But the ſeruile nature of ſome people is ſo ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh, that they will not feare the threatning of their Maſter, till they feele the Whip: our Lord there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth, as it were, ſhew vs the Rod, <hi>I will viſite,</hi> that is, puniſh and plague the worſhippers of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. According to the <hi>Pſalme</hi> 89. 32. <hi>If they breake my Statutes, and keepe not my Commandements: I will Viſite them with a rod, and their ſinnes with ſcourges.</hi> and in our owne language the Plague, and Gods Viſitation are vſuall Synonima's. <hi>The ſinnes of the fathers, on the children:</hi> here he allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to their being in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Whileſt your fathers were there (ſayth he) ſome of them, did worſhip ſome of thoſe Images: for the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Cow did teeme that Calfe of <hi>Iſrael. Ex.</hi> 32. I did winke at them: but I ſee you; and you ſhall feele mee. If you doe here, as they did there, worſhip Images, I will plague their ſinne on you: <hi>I will viſite the ſinnes of the fathers, vpon the children.</hi> Nor will I ſtay there: but as you propagate your children, ſo will I propagate my puniſhments: from the Father, to the Child, to the Grand-child, and to the Child after him. You ſhall ſuruiue, and your eyes ſhall ſee that propagated plague: <hi>I will viſite the ſinnes of the fathers, vpon the children, vnto the third and fourth generation.</hi> And for a moſt iuſt cauſe: becauſe the worſhippers of Images doe <hi>Hate mee.</hi> All ſinners in generall (and therefore Idolaters in ſpeciall) I haue proclaimed to bee my enemies, <hi>Malach.</hi> 2. 8. From theſe premiſes, he concludeth this Argument.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>You ſhould feare to commit that ſinne, which doth cauſe you to hate God, and God to plague you,</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:22564:8"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>for the fathers, in the children, and on your owne perſons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>But the worſhipping of Images is a ſinne, which doth cauſe you to hate God, and God to plague you, to viſite you: from the fathers, to their children: euen to the third and fourth genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore you ſhould feare to worſhip Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This fearefull puniſhment, is ſuch a fearefull Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: that mee thinketh, it ſhould make the eare to tingle, and the heart to tremble, of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which doth but bow to an Image: if he doth but heare theſe words pronounced. <hi>If you doe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Images,</hi> on ſuch <hi>I will viſite the ſinnes of the fathers, vpon the children, vnto the third and fourth generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, although in a bad cauſe, <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> could not perſwade <hi>Fabritius,</hi> neither by affrighting him with his Elephant, nor by alluring him with his gold: yet, in a good cauſe, many are more moued with Gods mercies, than forced with his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. I conceiue therefore that the moſt weightie argument, lieth here in the bottome of my Text: where Gods goodneſſe is propoſed vnto vs in three branches: the Qualitie, <hi>I will ſhew mercy,</hi> in the <hi>Poſtills</hi> phraſe, mercy of Confection, mercy of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and mercy of Perfection: that is, all Gods mercies in regard of our Creation, Regeneration, and Glorification: ſhall bee conferred vpon, and confirmd vnto, ſuch as will not worſhip Images, The Quantitie, Gods mercy, is like a Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call line, ſhot throughout the whole world: hee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22564:9"/> will <hi>ſhew mercy vnto Thouſands,</hi> vnto ſuch as will not worſhip Images. The Qualification: for Gods Goodneſſe, as he doth ſhew it, ſo his ſeruants may know it, that they ſhall haue it, by a ſure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: by a token Impreſſed, if they <hi>loue mee:</hi> and Expreſſed, if they <hi>keepe my Commandements.</hi> To ſuch as <hi>loue mee,</hi> and <hi>keepe my Commandements, I will ſhew mercy: if—they will not worſhip Images.</hi> So from Gods Goodneſſe conſidered three wayes, we may conſider three Arguments, againſt Images: <hi>in Theſi, in Antitheſi, &amp; Hypotheſi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In Theſi: <hi>If thou doest deſire my Mercy, thou ſhalt not worſhip Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But thou doest deſire my Mercy.</hi> Therefore, <hi>Thou ſhalt not worſhip Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In Antitheſi: <hi>If thou doeſt deſire my Mercies, a thouſand times ſurpaſsing my Iudgements, Thou ſhalt not worſhip Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But thou doeſt deſire my Mercies, a thouſand times ſurpaſsing my Iudgements, theſe being but to the fourth, thoſe to a thouſand genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not worſhip Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. From Gods Goodneſſe, <hi>in Hypotheſi,</hi> we may frame an Hypotheticall Syllogiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If thou doeſt loue me, and wilt keepe my Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: Then wilt thou not worſhip Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But I know, thou doeſt loue mee, and wilt keepe my Commandements.</hi> Therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know, Thou wilt not worſhip Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To inuolue all in one: If there bee a <hi>Gehenna,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:22564:9"/> and a Paradiſe: if there be an Hell, and an Heauen prepared: then dare not wretched men be ſo deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate of the one, and ſo preſumptuous of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but they will be perſwaded, <hi>not to worſhip Images.</hi> But if they <hi>will worſhip Images,</hi> let them looke for <hi>poena ſenſus,</hi> and <hi>poena damni:</hi> let them be aſſured to loſe the one, and to feele the other. <hi>For—I the Lord thy God, am a iealous God, and viſit the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the children, vnto the third and fourth generation, in them that hate mee.</hi> Although <hi>I ſhew mercie vnto thouſands, in them that loue me, and keepe my Commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let mee craue your patience, that I may reade ouer my long Text, once more: <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe, any grauen Image, nor any like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of any thing in Heauen aboue, or in the Earth beneath, or in the water vnder the Earth: thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, nor worſhip them, For I the Lord thy God, am a iealous God, viſiting the ſinnes of the fathers, vpon the children, vnto the third and fourth Generation in them that hate mee, but ſhew mercie vnto thouſands in them that loue mee, and keepe my Commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Sicilians</hi> accuſed <hi>Verres</hi> of Briberie, <hi>Tully</hi> (being entertained their Lawier) omitted his vſuall Oratorie, and Rhetoricall Oration, onely putting the Caſe in plaine tearmes, produced the witneſſes, and ſaid, This is his crime, and our accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation: Let who can gainſay this euident tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. <hi>Hortenſius</hi> the others Aduocate, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the cleereneſſe of the Caſe, and manifeſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, refuſed to plead one ſyllable in the defence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22564:10"/> thereof: and <hi>Verres</hi> yeelded himſelfe vnto a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie baniſhment.</p>
            <p>Had the Patrons of <hi>Images,</hi> but the honeſt baſhfulneſſe of Heathen <hi>Hortenſius:</hi> and were the conſciences of thoſe we challenge for worſhipping them, no more confident then <hi>Verres</hi> himſelfe: I ſhould make no queſtion, but that onely the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this plaine Precept againſt <hi>Images,</hi> would make the Learned bluſh to plead for ſo plaine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie: and cauſe the common people, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon worſhipper of <hi>Images</hi> to recant, and make a voluntarie ſubmiſſion.</p>
            <p>But alas wee conteſt with men, reſolued to hold the concluſion: who ſhame not to ſupport a ſhamefull ſinne, againſt the very Letter of the Law. I am inforced therefore, to inforce my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation: wherein I muſt act two perſons, firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: firſt, I will ſhew what they can ſay <hi>for Images:</hi> and next what wee can ſay <hi>against Images;</hi> both: truly, painly, impartial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; euen as I hope to plead, my owne ſelfe, for my owne ſoule, before our great God, at his dreadfull Day of judgement.</p>
            <p>Our Aduerſaries are like the <hi>Thebans: Quot ſunt Thebarum portae,</hi> they haue ſeuen Bulwarkes, whence they propugne their <hi>Images:</hi> the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialls whereof they pretend, all to be fetched from this Commandement.</p>
            <p>All their Arguments, and Anſweres are raiſed from theſe ſeuen Heads: from the conſideration of the <hi>Agent,</hi> of the <hi>Action,</hi> of the <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> of the <hi>Worke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> of the <hi>Obiect,</hi> of a <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:22564:10"/> 
               <hi>propounded,</hi> and of <hi>this Commandement expounded.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image: We doe not,</hi> ſay they: <hi>God doth giue vs patternes, and is our Patron,</hi> God himſelfe did make them. Secondly, Neither doe we make them <hi>to our Selues,</hi> we haue a Warrant from Heauen, both ordinarie, and extraordinarie: he hath granted leaue by the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Images</hi> with many glorious <hi>Miracles.</hi> Thirdly, That <hi>Instrument</hi> of our adoring God, is an <hi>Image,</hi> not an <hi>Idoll,</hi> as the Heretickes miſtake it, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call it: no <hi>Idoll,</hi> therefore no <hi>Idolatrie.</hi> Fourthly, We doe not <hi>Worſhip</hi> them, it is not godly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour we giue them, but Reuerence, or Veneration. Fiftly, For our Religious Worſhip reſteth not in them, but reflecteth on him: it is <hi>God wee worſhip, and not the Image.</hi> Sixtly, Wee haue a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, equall to this Commandement, <hi>Pari pietatis affictu veneramur,</hi> The Tradition of an vn-erring Church to iuſtifie our action. Seuenthly, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Trident ſub Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 3. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 4.</note> and laſtly, this very Commandement (ſo much vrged againſt vs) it is either <hi>included,</hi> and but a part of the firſt Commandement: or <hi>excluded,</hi> and no part of the perpetuall Morall Law: it being onely Poſitiue, for that Place and People. They diſpute then, from <hi>Examples,</hi> from <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>Miracles,</hi> from the <hi>name</hi> of an <hi>Idoll,</hi> from the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Adoration;</hi> from the <hi>Perſon adored,</hi> from <hi>Tradition,</hi> and from the <hi>Expoſition of this ſecond Commandement.</hi> Thus haue wee viewed the Heads of their Troupes: I will now diſcouer their ſeuerall Files and Rankes, that you may ſee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22564:11"/> the Armie of our Aduerſaries, which defend their <hi>Diana dropped from Heauen,</hi> their <hi>Cruſadoes,</hi> which fight for their <hi>Croſſes,</hi> and worſhipping of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their Examples, giue the on-ſet: of the <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſilium ſui redit. ſect.</hi> 20.</note> in Gods Houſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. 18. and of the <hi>Lions</hi> in the Kings houſe, 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 10. 19. alleaged by the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Imag. lib.</hi> 2.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> of the <hi>Brazen Serpent Numb.</hi> 21. 8. by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and a whole Colledge of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites,</hi> haue concluded out of <hi>Daniel.</hi> 3. 1. that, as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rhemiſts in Reu.</hi> 9. 14.</note> that Image was for the honour of the King: ſo their Images were for the honour of Chriſt. Nay, the Image of Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> was made by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell: and the Image of <hi>Ediſſa,</hi> by Chriſt himſelfe, ſaith <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Theſe Examples (I ſay) gaue the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Imagin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note> on-ſet, and indeed they are like the forlorne Hopes quickly cut in pieces: or rather like honeſt Subiects, forced to the fight againſt their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne, they turne their Weapons vpon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, which bring them to the Battell. Conſider the <hi>Author,</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> of all theſe Images. For the firſt: when the Image-worſhippers are as wiſe as <hi>Solomon,</hi> and as pure as Angels, hauing the ſame authoritie with Chriſt, from God: then may they doe, what they ſay theſe did, erect Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to religious vſes. Notwithſtanding theſe were neuer made for Adoration. The two laſt, the Image of Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> and of <hi>Ediſſa,</hi> were not made, I meane by thoſe Artiſts: the other were made, but not worſhipped. The <hi>Lions</hi> were in the Kings Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, whither the people did come, but not to worſhip: the <hi>Cherubins</hi> were in the <hi>Sanctum San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:22564:11"/> whither the people did not come. But the <hi>Serpent,</hi> is an vnanſwerable inſtance, againe Image Adoration: for ſo ſoone as it was adored, it was damned for an Idoll, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 31. 1. All theſe Examples therefore, are impertinent, that one only excepted of <hi>Nebuchadnezzer:</hi> which was worſhipped at <hi>Babell,</hi> as an Idoll: and therein I confeſſe, their Images doe anſwere that Example.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, they inſtance in the ſecond phraſe, we doe not (ſay they) make any Images to our ſelues, wee haue a warrant from God, to worſhip them. Wee haue his warrant ordinarie: his Word and Oracle, and his warrant extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, his Workes and Miracles. The ordinarie warrant they ſeeme to repute, but an ordinarie Argument, they vrge the Scriptures very ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suarez Apol. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11, 12, 13, <hi>&amp; &amp;</hi> 14.</note> Learned <hi>Suarez</hi> in his large Diſcourſe of <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> alleadgeth not one Scripture, to auouch the Adoration of them. Seuen indeed are cited by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine:</hi> but ſo, as that I cannot tell which to admire moſt: either the firſt, that the Scriptures are not quoted: or the laſt, that they are ſo ill quoted; by two of our learnedſt Aduerſaries, in the greateſt point in Controuerſie: they accuſing vs for Hereſie, becauſe wee oppugne; and wee them for <hi>Idolatry,</hi> becauſe they propugne the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of <hi>Images. Suarez</hi> his Scriptures, are ſoone aſſailed, becauſe neuer cited. Take <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> teſtimonies, according to his owne corrupt Tranſlation, and make the beſt of them. <hi>Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſcabellum,</hi> Worſhip his foot ſtoole. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. <hi>Nolite iurare per Coelum, Matth.</hi> 5. Sweare not by Heanen. <hi>Locus in quo ſtas terra ſancta est,</hi> The
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22564:12"/> place wherein thou ſtandeſt is holy ground, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. The Paſſeouer is called, <hi>Dies ſancta, &amp; venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis;</hi> A holy, and reuerend Day, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. The Prieſts apparell is called, <hi>Vestis ſanctae,</hi> Holy Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. The Graue of Chriſt is called, <hi>Glorioſum Sepulchrum;</hi> A glorious Sepulchre, <hi>Eſay</hi> 11. And the Scriptures are called, <hi>Sacrae Literae;</hi> Holy Writings, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. How any ingenious indifferent perſon, can frame from theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, any concluſion, conſequence, or collection, for the worſhipping of Images: this ſurpaſſeth my imagination.</p>
            <p>But the truth is, they are not very confident in the Scriptures: but in Miracles they place extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie confidence, in this extraordinarie War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. This Argument is vſed by <hi>Coster, Bellarmine, Suarez;</hi> and almoſt by all on that ſide. A Brazen <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coſterus Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridion, p.</hi> 442.</note> Image was erected by that woman, whoſe bloudie iſſue was ſtopped by Chriſt, vnder which grew a <hi>Panacea,</hi> an hearbe that healed all diſeaſes: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Images are to bee worſhipped, ſaith <hi>Coſterus.</hi> Another Image of Chriſt, was ſmote thorough by a <hi>Iew:</hi> and out of that wound iſſued bloud, which cured many diſeaſes: therefore <hi>Images</hi> are to be worſhipped, ſaith <hi>Bellarmine. Theoph. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> could not die till hee had adored the <hi>Image</hi> of Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> whom hee had hated <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suarez Apol. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11 <hi>ſect.</hi> 19. <hi>Down.</hi> of <hi>Anti. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>ſect.</hi> 6.</note> in his life; and therefore <hi>Images</hi> are to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, ſaith <hi>Suarez.</hi> Pretie Stories: I will tell you a few more of them. An <hi>Engliſh Image</hi> at <hi>Cheſter,</hi> moued the Hand, as if hee had bleſſed the people. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sheldon. Mot.</hi> 5.</note> A <hi>French Image</hi> at Saint <hi>Omers,</hi> remoued it ſelfe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22564:12"/> to a place fitter for Adoration. A <hi>Spaniſh Image,</hi> went in the night to viſit the ſicke. And many <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian Images</hi> haue been ſeene to weep grieuouſly, when the ſprigs of new cut Vines, haue prompted <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hisp. Conuerſ. pag.</hi> 19. Relation of the Religion, <hi>ſect.</hi> 44.</note> them to ſuch tragical teares. Neither is the ſtory of the <hi>Florentine Image,</hi> altogether vnknowne, nor altogether vnbeleeued. Before which, when as <hi>Gio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanni Gualber to</hi> did proſtrate himſelfe, holding in his hand his mortall enemie, whom he proteſted that he there forgaue, as hee did deſire himſelfe to bee forgiuen by Chriſt. Then did the Crucifixe bow downe his head, with a gracious approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and for the eternall memorie, of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocall charitie, the Image doth ſtand with the head bowed vnto this preſent houre. Peraduenture theſe Stories may bee cenſured for <hi>Apocryphall:</hi> I <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De vita Sancti Hyacinthij, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.</note> will therefore adde one or two out of Claſſicall Authours. <hi>Seuerinus</hi> ſaith, in <hi>Kiouia,</hi> there was a goodly ſtone Statue, of the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> ſome ſixe hundred weight and vpward. When <hi>Hyacinthus</hi> fled from the incurſion made by the <hi>Tartars, Runnest thou!</hi> and leaueſt me to the furie of the Barbarous? quoth the <hi>Image.</hi> Alas, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Lady,</hi> replyed he, thy <hi>Image</hi> is too heauie, to carrie with me. Try, quoth the <hi>Image;</hi> and vpon the tryall, he found it as light as a Reed, and went with it dry foot, ouer the great Riuer <hi>Boryſtenes,</hi> to the great Citie <hi>Cracouia.</hi> In the life of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquine,</hi> it is related that when <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> did pray before a Crucifix at <hi>Naples,</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> did anſwere him, <hi>Bene ſcripſiſti de me Thoma:</hi> Thou haſt written very well of me good <hi>Thomas.</hi> Doe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22564:13"/> not al theſe Examples, merit one concluſion? <hi>Ergo: Images are to be worſhipped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let vs conſult a little, before wee conclude; <hi>Falſa, ficta, fucata omnia:</hi> almoſt all theſe, and all ſuch, are meere Lyes: and none to the purpoſe, for the proofe of Adoration. Grant that they were true: yet looke back wards, the <hi>Heathen</hi> had Miracles for the confirmation of their Idolatrie, faith <hi>Valerius Maximus.</hi> Their Prieſts did ſpeake <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Valer. Max. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Theodoretus lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> through their <hi>Images,</hi> ſaith <hi>Theodoret.</hi> The <hi>Palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> did <hi>Vibrare hastam,</hi> ſhake her Speare, and mooue her eyes, and the <hi>Mirabilarij,</hi> could plead Miracles, though Heretickes. Then looke for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall alſo <hi>eſtabliſh his doctrine by Miracles,</hi> 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 9. Conclude wee therefore in Gods owne phraſe: <hi>Though men ſhould doe ſignes and wonders, yet must they not perſwade vs to Idolatrie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this cauſe the Patrons of <hi>Images,</hi> are like the <hi>Low-countrey</hi> Souldiers: they deſire a <hi>Defenſiue,</hi> rather than an <hi>Offenſiue</hi> Warre. If they but keepe ground in this Queſtion, they thinke they get ground in their Religion. Hence they fortifie themſelues with ſuch Diſtinctions, as that it is as eaſie to diſcerne a <hi>Camelion</hi> with the Eye, a <hi>Proteus</hi> with the Hand, and a <hi>Sphinx</hi> with the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as to vnderſtand, and leaſt to diſplay their more ſubtilties. Firſt, they diſtinguiſh of the word <hi>Image,</hi> and <hi>Idoll: Iohn Roberts</hi> the <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob. Rob. Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturae Eccleſ. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gl Art.</hi> 22. <hi>Prop,</hi> 3.</note> when he hath alleadged eight and twentie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, alleadged by vs againſt <hi>Images:</hi> he ſuddenly blotteth them all out, with this one Diſtinction.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22564:13"/> 
               <hi>Nihil habeo quod reſpondeam, niſi quodtoties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſum eſt a Catholicis: non agi ijs locis de Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, ſed de Idolis.</hi> That this Commandement, and thoſe Scriptures, condemne onely the <hi>Idols</hi> of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> and not the <hi>Images</hi> of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians!</hi> where let vs vnderſtand what an <hi>Idoll</hi> is. <hi>Imago est ſimilitudo rei Verae, Idolum falſae,</hi> ſaith <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. de Imag. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>P. Lumbard. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>diſt.</hi> 37.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine:</hi> That is an <hi>Image</hi> is the likeneſſe of a true thing, an <hi>Idoll</hi> of a thing feigned. The Maſter of the <hi>Sentences</hi> hath this Diſtinction alſo.</p>
            <p>This Diſtinction; doth both excuſe the <hi>Pagans,</hi> and accuſe themſelues of <hi>Idolatry.</hi> Who dareth challenge the <hi>Heathens,</hi> that thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Images</hi> did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Chimaeras,</hi> and Fictions. Were not the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Moone, Bodies?</hi> the <hi>Cats</hi> and <hi>Crocodiles, Beaſts? Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturne, Men?</hi> all <hi>Creatures?</hi> and therefore the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of them, were <hi>Images,</hi> and not <hi>Idols.</hi> But our Aduerſaries themſelues, haue not they <hi>Saints,</hi> which were neuer in the World? as Saint <hi>Longinus,</hi> Saint <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> Saint <hi>Martiall,</hi> Saint <hi>Vrſula,</hi> Saint <hi>Catharine,</hi> Saint <hi>Margaret, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore their repreſentations are not <hi>Images,</hi> but <hi>Idols;</hi> according to their owne Diſtinction.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, that this inhibition is abſolute of all <hi>Images,</hi> and not reſpectiue of <hi>Idols</hi> onely, it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent from theſe foure conſiderations: <hi>A voce, extenſione, fine, &amp; ratione precepti:</hi> From the Word of the Precept, from the Extenſion of the Precept, from the Scope of the Precept, and from the Reaſon of the Precept. Firſt, the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Peſel.</note> (as I haue touched alreadie) is tranſlated, both an
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22564:14"/> 
               <hi>Idoll,</hi> and an <hi>Image</hi> alſo: Againe, the <hi>Septuagints</hi> ſet forth by the authoritie of <hi>Pius</hi> the Fift, tearme the Statues of <hi>Baal,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Images,</hi> 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 11. 18. but 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 23. 7. they call them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Idols.</hi> And their owne learned Cardinall <hi>Caietane,</hi> confeſſeth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. de Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 2027.</note> that theſe two words <hi>Image,</hi> and <hi>Idoll</hi> are confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Therefore it is a vaine Diſtinction. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The Interdiction is Vniuerſall: <hi>any likeneſſe, of any thing, in Heauen, Earth, or Sea.</hi> Now the <hi>Romiſh Images,</hi> are they not ſome likeneſſe of ſome thing, either in Heauen, or in the Earth, or in the Sea? how can they be exempted, from this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inhibition. Thirdly, the End, ſcope, and drift of this Commandement, is to preſerue religious worſhip to God alone: it muſt not therefore bee imparted to any creature, whether it be to an Idol, or an Image: whether it be by a Pagan, or a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Nay the profeſſion doth aggrauate the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 14. Fourthly, the Reaſon of the precept is this: <hi>For I am a iealous God.</hi> Now will the iealous man, permit the Honour of his Bed, to Some men, by way of Difference? No more will God permit the Honour of his Worſhip, to ſome Images, by way of Diſtinction.</p>
            <p>Adde to this that Logicall axiome, <hi>Cui conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit definitio, conuenit definitum:</hi> ſuch as haue the ſame Definition, are the ſame Thing: but the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Images, and the Heathen Idolls, haue the ſame Definition; therefore they are the ſame thing. Thus <hi>Dauid</hi> doth define them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135. 15. <hi>The I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of the Heathen, are but ſiluer and gold, the worke of mens hands: They haue mouthes and ſpeake</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:22564:14"/> 
               <hi>not, and eyes haue they and ſee not: they haue eares, and heare not: neither is there any breath in their mouthes.</hi> But the Romiſh Images, are but Siluer and Gold, and the worke of mens hands: they haue mouthes and ſpeake not: and eyes haue they and ſee not: they haue eares and heare not: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any breath in their mouthes. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Images of the Romiſh Catholikes, and the Idolls of the Pagans, are all one without Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</p>
            <p>I will ſhut vp this point with the ſaying of <hi>Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardus;</hi> p. 237. <hi>Si Sanctorum imagines, hi qui Doemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num cultum reliquerunt, Venerari <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uberentur: puto quod videretur ijs, non tam idola reliquiſſe, quam ſimulacra mutaſſe,</hi> that is, If the Pagans ſhould bee perſwaded, to leaue worſhipping<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Images of their Heathen Gods, and to wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ip the Images of our Chriſtian Saints: they would ſuppoſe, that they did not forſake, but alter their Adoration of Images.</p>
            <p>By this we ſee that there are <hi>Idolls</hi> in <hi>Rome:</hi> but for <hi>Idolatry,</hi> this they obſcure with a cloud of quaint diſtinctions, which I cannot ſay whether they be more infinite, or intricate: yet this I ſay; firſt, that their Armie of Diſtinctions are very <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianites,</hi> they deſtroy one another. Againe, as the <hi>Sepia,</hi> by powring out her inkie puddle, doth ſo dazle the eye of the Fiſher, that hee cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the bodie of the Fiſh: yet by the very acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hee knoweth more certainely the place where about ſhee lurketh. So their many perplexed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, make vnderſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen, the more
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22564:15"/> aſſured of their errours, and Idolatrie (they would not thus ſtruggle, and wind about, with their ſnap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping diſtinctions, to bite in ſunder the thread of our arguments: but that they feele themſelues en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrapped, and faſt bound with theſe manifold cords of Scripture, and reaſon, choaking their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) though I confeſſe that their nicities, will exerciſe a ſound iudgement punctually to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer them.</p>
            <p>Although wee ſay, they haue Idolls: yet they ſay, they doe not worſhip them. With <hi>Dulia</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture, <note place="margin">Conſilium ſui Reditus.</note> but not with <hi>Latria,</hi> ſaith <hi>Spalato.</hi> Nay, neither with <hi>Dulia,</hi> nor <hi>Latria,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> vnleſſe it be <hi>Analogice</hi> and <hi>Reductiuè.</hi> Yea Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> are to be adored, both with <hi>Dulia,</hi> and <hi>Latria,</hi> and <hi>Hyperdulia</hi> alſo, ſaith <hi>A. D.</hi> but <hi>improprie, per</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A. D. Sect.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>accidence &amp; analogice.</hi> Againe, all worſhip is to be exhibited to all Images, <hi>Deriuatiue,</hi> not <hi>Primitiue,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Enchirid. c.</hi> 13.</note> ſaith <hi>Caſterus. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncino</hi> would haue them to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped <hi>Relatiuè,</hi> only in regard of their repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trent. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 799.</note> 
               <hi>Lainez</hi> liketh not that reſtitution, but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that they may be worſhipped <hi>Obiectiuè,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Trad. par.</hi> 3.</note> of their dedication alſo. <hi>Pereſius</hi> ſaith, that veneration ought to be onely <hi>Motiuè:</hi> but <hi>Sayrus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clauis li.</hi> 4. <hi>c</hi> 30.</note> 
               <hi>Inhaeſiue,</hi> that they are truely venerable.</p>
            <p>Concerning this multitude of diſtinctions, I will apply that ſaying of <hi>Cicero:</hi> as it is alreadie <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iewell in H. Art.</hi> 4. <hi>Sect.</hi> 12.</note> applyed by Biſhop <hi>Iewell; Bonum eſſe negus: Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum dicis: An minuis hoc pacto Auaritiam?</hi> thou wilt not haue wealth, called <hi>Bonum,</hi> but <hi>Praepoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum:</hi> but doeſt thou hereby any thing abate aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice? Euen ſo ſay wee to our aduerſaries, yee will
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22564:15"/> not haue the worſhipping of Images be called <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria,</hi> but <hi>Dulia:</hi> but doe they hereby any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Idolatrie? Or to come cloſer to their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in the words of our Souereigne: When <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Praemonit. p.</hi> 41.</note> Chriſt at the day of Iudgement ſhall accuſe, them for Idolatry, I doubt whither hee will be ſatisfied, by ſuch nice ſophiſtical diſtinctions. <hi>Haec ſunt verba</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suarez Ap. li.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>num.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>regis: Quibus prudenter obuiare mihi difficilius eſt, quàm clariſsimis rationibus reſpondere:</hi> ſaith <hi>Suarez,</hi> his words ſpeake the truth; that he found it more eaſie to aſſoile the moſt learned argument, then to anſwer this plaine appealing to his conſcience, and indeed the plaine conſcience of a poore ſinner, dare not depend on ſuch curious diſtinctions againſt the day of Iudgement.</p>
            <p>To proceed; although the Heads of theſe Fox-like diſtinctions, bee diuided: yet all their Tales meet in this concurrance; that they do not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhip Images; not with <hi>Latria,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> calleth it, or with godly worſhip, as our Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Engliſh it. I anſwere, that euen <hi>Dulia,</hi> or <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rhemiſts in Act.</hi> 17. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</note> the loweſt degree of Diuine worſhip is inhibited by God: as the onely bowing of the knee, in this Commandement, and alſo <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 1. Againe, I ſay, that <hi>Latria</hi> it Selfe, or the higheſt degree of godly worſhip, is exhibited by ſome of them vnto Images. The Image of Chriſt is to be adored <hi>ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione Latriae,</hi> with the very worſhip due to God: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sum. part.</hi> 3. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 25. <hi>Art.</hi> 3.</note> theſe are the very words of <hi>Thomas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This alſo is the ſuffrage of all the <hi>Thomiſts,</hi> ſaith <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtitut. part.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Azorius;</hi> yea, it is the definitiue ſentence of a greater than <hi>Thomas,</hi> or all the <hi>Thomiſts,</hi> euen of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22564:16"/> the Pope himſelfe. <hi>Clemens</hi> the eight ſpake thus, <hi>Crux Legati, quia ei debetur Latria, erit à dextris:</hi> that is, The Croſſe muſt haue the right hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is worſhipped with Gods owne worſhip.</p>
            <p>If they mince the matter with more diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: I anſwer in the words of one of their own, an Engliſh-man, the Author of the <hi>Monarchomachia,</hi> that the plaine people ſtand not to weigh words, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 49.</note> but they take them <hi>in cortice,</hi> as the letter impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: or in the words of another, their owne too, an <hi>Italian, Bellarmine. Coguntur vti ſubtiliſsimis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctionibus, quas ipſi vix intelligunt, nedum popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De imagin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 22. <hi>p.</hi> 2078.</note> 
               <hi>imperitus.</hi> They are conſtrained to ſhift vs off with ſuch ſubtile diſtinctions, as their Doctors themſelues can hardly vnderſtand, and therefore much leſſe the poore plaine people. Againe (if we bee ſo liberall as to grant that) the Learned may worſhip God with <hi>Latria,</hi> and his Image at the ſame time, with an inferiour kind of the ſame wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: Be it, I ſay, that their Learned may make ſuch Mathematicall abſtractions, and haue a diuerſitie of the manner, in the identitie of the action of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration: They, forſooth, can doe it: but can they make the common people ſo Metaphyſicall?</p>
            <p>And for the People! all their kiſſing, creeping, crouching, proſtrations, inuocations, proceſſions, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coſterus Enchi. c.</hi> 13.</note> pilgrimages, &amp;c. Are all theſe, no part of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? Let them cleere this, and I will confeſſe, that they haue no Idols, and are no Idolaters.</p>
            <p>Thus farre haue wee followed them, and haue found, that amongſt them there are <hi>Idola,</hi> Idols; and <hi>Latria,</hi> worſhip: yet, ſay they, there is not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22564:16"/> 
               <hi>Idololatria,</hi> no Idolatry. Becauſe they giue not this worſhip, to thoſe Idolls, <hi>tanquam Dijs,</hi> as if <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sayrus, Clau. Conſcientie. lib</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</note> they were very Gods. The Idolatry, which we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, they excuſe, by diſtinguiſhing of the Obiect: in the adoration of Images, wee doe not (ſay they) adore them, but Him; not That image of God, but God in that Image. And ſo they ſay of their <hi>Saints</hi> alſo, and their <hi>Images. Lignum non adoramus, ſed in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Duraeus in Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tak. pag.</hi> 424.</note> 
               <hi>ligno adoramus eum qui in ligno pro nobis pependit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Duraeus:</hi> that is, we doe not worſhip the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixe, but the Crucified: not the Croſſe, but in the Croſſe, he who was hanged on the Croſſe for vs, is adored by vs. To which purpoſe is that diſtich.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Effigiem Chriſti cum cernis, pronus adora:</l>
               <l>Non tamen effigiem, ſed quod deſignat, honora.</l>
            </q>
            <p>When thou doeſt ſee the Croſſe, full low Adore:</p>
            <p>Not it, but Him, the Croſſe for thee once bore.</p>
            <p>The phraſe of my Text will fit them for an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: <hi>I am a iealous God.</hi> Such is the way of the adulterous woman: <hi>Shee eateth, and wipeth her mouth, and ſaith, I haue done no wickedneſſe,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs 30. 20.</p>
            <p>If inceſtuous <hi>Clodia</hi> had diſtinguiſhed, that ſhee receiued <hi>Clodius</hi> into her bed, but <hi>tanquam fratrem,</hi> not <hi>tanquam maritum</hi> (only as her Brother, not ſo intirely as her Husband) her husband <hi>Metellus</hi> it would hardly haue excuſed her of Adulterie. No more will God, thoſe who ſhall plead <hi>Tanquam Deum:</hi> that indeed they worſhip Images, but not as if That Image were God Himſelfe.</p>
            <p>But I anſwere three waies: Firſt, All the old
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22564:17"/> Idolaters did not adore their Images, as Gods: and yet they were Idolaters notwithſtanding. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Though our Aduerſaries doe worſhip the Saints, and God in their Images, yet are they Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters. Thirdly, That they doe worſhip the verie Image, and ſome of them ſo, as if it were God Himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, admit that ſome of the Heathen were ſo groſſe, as to thinke their Images to haue beene ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Gods: yet all were not ſo. The <hi>Thebaides</hi> did <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rainolds de Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lolatria lib.</hi> 2. 6. 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 48.</note> worſhip their God (though pictured like a man) whom they called <hi>Cneph,</hi> eſteemed immortall, and proclaimed the Creatour of the round World, and of all that therein is. <hi>Iulians</hi> anſwere is obuious, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanchius in pracept.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Non lapidem Iouem, ſed Iouem in lapide;</hi> That hee did worſhip God in that Statue, not that Statue as God. And it was the crime of the Heathen Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, that they did worſhip God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Image of a man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 23. But the Idolatrous Iewes exclude all euaſion, <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> 20. 23. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Thou ſhalt not <note place="margin">Lo Lechem Lo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ti.</note> make any Image To thee, nor With mee, that is, neither to bee worſhipped as God, nor yet with God. Moreouer, in <hi>Exodus</hi> 32. ponder three things: firſt, the <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> verſe the firſt, the Calfe is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to <hi>Moſes,</hi> which ſhould goe before them in his ſtead, and as hee did; as a Viſible Vice-gerent of God. Secondly, weigh the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> in the fourth verſe, <hi>Theſe are thy Gods, O Iſrael, Qui eduxerunt te de terra Aeygpti:</hi> theſe are thy Gods O Iſrael, <hi>which brought thee out of the Land of Aegypt.</hi> Now our fiction cannot faſten ſuch a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidneſſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22564:17"/> on that people, that they ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that Calfe, which they made that Day, to haue brought them out of the Land of Aegypt four months before. Thirdly, conſider the <hi>Entheſis,</hi> or <hi>Ectheſis</hi> in the fift verſe, <hi>Cras erit ſolenitas</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to morrow ſhall bee a feaſt to <hi>Iehoua,</hi> the Proper name of the Hebrew God. Finally it is confeſſed <note place="margin">Catech. Tvi. in prac. primum.</note> by their owne Catechiſme, that the Iſraelites did adore God in the Calfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuppoſe that our Aduerſaries do not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore their Images, but their Saints in their Images; Yet cannot they thereby acquite themſelues from Idolatrie, indeed from a double Idolatrie: Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, becauſe in worſhipping Images, they worſhip Men, <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 26. or Angells, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19. 10. and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, becauſe in worſhipping the Saints, they do that worſhip to Images, which is forbidden by God, they Bow to them, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 1. And if they worſhip God in the Image, there alſo is a twofold tranſgreſſion: Firſt, they make his Image, againſt his expreſſe inhibition, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4, 15. Next, <hi>Adorare Deum in ſigno non proprio, est Idololatria,</hi> ſaith <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſiodoras;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Altiſ. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 15.</note> The Adoration of God in an Image (or ſigne) which God hath not appointed, is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, wee charge them, that ſome of them doe worſhip Images, as if they were very Gods. Some indeed doe extenuate their palpable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and (eſpecially in diſcourſe and diſputation) they will tell you, that they worſhip, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. But our <hi>Sayrus</hi> informeth their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clauis Conſc. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 11.</note> otherwiſe, that the very Images are to bee adored.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:22564:18"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſpeaketh yet broader: that they doe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 21.</note> not worſhip <hi>tantùm, coram, per, &amp; in:</hi> onely Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, By, or In the Image: but that they giue their worſhip to the very Image, as men doe their almes to the Poore: and that, <hi>Ipſae Imagines terminant venerationem,</hi> that their worſhip doth reſt in the Image. Yet <hi>lacobus Naclantus</hi> (as hee is quoted, by <note place="margin">Homilie of Idolatrie, <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 71.</note> our excellent Homily againſt Idolatrie) out-draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him in his owne Bow, and is more bold, and broad than <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe, in the behalfe of Image-adoration. <hi>Non ſolum fatendum est fideles in Eccleſia adorare, coram Imagine (vt nonnulli ad cautelam forte loquuntur) ſed &amp; adorare Imaginem ſine quo volueris ſcrupulo.</hi> Some (ſayth he) ſay that wee worſhip, onely before the Image (which they ſpeake cautelouſly) but we adore the Image it ſelfe, without any manner of ſcruple.</p>
            <p>Proceed wee from their Poſitions, to their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice: and we ſhall perceiue that ſome of them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the very Image. Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> woman is one, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rainoldus de Idol. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 70.</note> who prayed to the Image of our Ladie, that it would intercede for her, to the perſon of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: as it is related by that reuerend Diuine, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Rainolds.</hi> Their owne <hi>Italian</hi> women are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: who worſhipped the Image of the Ladie <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netana</hi> of <hi>Florence, tanquam pluuiae, ſerenitatiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Donatricem,</hi> as the very Authour of Raine and Faire-weather. The inſtance is authenticall: a Pope is my Authour, <hi>Pius ſecundus.</hi> Moreouer, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coment. Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 2.</note> they vtter Prayers to their Pictures, which cannot concerne the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or thing Reſembled: Thus they Pray to the Croſſe.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:22564:18"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ara Crucis,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Salue lignum</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Breuiar. Rom. part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Hye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>al. fine.</note>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Lampas lucis,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Vitae, dignum</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Vera ſalus Hominum:</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ferre mundi pretium:</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nobis pronum,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Confer iſti</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Fac Patronum,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Plebi Chriſti,</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quem tuliſti Dominum.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Crucis Beneficium.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>O Altar bright,</cell>
                     <cell>Haile holy Wood</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Lampe of light,</cell>
                     <cell>Of life: the Rood</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Thou hope of our ſaluation:</cell>
                     <cell>Of peareleſſe eſtimation:</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Cauſe him to heare,</cell>
                     <cell>Of thy good grace,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>whom thou didſt beare,</cell>
                     <cell>Bleſſe this whole place,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To free vs from damnation.</cell>
                     <cell>And goodly congregation.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>That the Croſſe ſhould intercede to Chriſt: this Prayer cannot be to Chriſt, but to the Croſſe it ſelfe. Theſe words alſo are ſpoken directly to the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cloth, and to the Image: and are not agreeable to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Salue ſancta facies noſtri Redemptoris:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moulins Buck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſect.</hi> 120. <hi>pag.</hi> 321.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In qua nitit ſpecies, diuini ſplendoris:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Impreſſa panniculo niuei candoris:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Salue vultus Domini, Imago beata:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deduc ad proprium, O foelix figura:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ad videndum faciem, quae est Chriſti pura.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Haile holy face, of Chriſt Redeemer mine,</l>
               <l>In which the ſparkes of heauen it ſelfe doe ſhine,</l>
               <l>Here pictur'd in pure linnen white and fine.</l>
               <l>Haile bleſſed Image of that bleſſed face,</l>
               <l>Of Chriſt himſelfe: O bring mee to that place,</l>
               <l>Where His face I may ſee, by Thy ſweet grace.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Neither may we paſſe their <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22564:19"/> they are permitted to pray vnto an Image, euen by <note place="margin">Catech. Trid. Tract. de Orat. Tit. Quis Oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note> their <hi>Trent</hi> Catechiſme.</p>
            <p>To come to a concluſion of this point: <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> himſelfe doth grant, that Chriſtians haue worſhipped the very Images, and that with Diuine <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. de Imag. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> Honour: and he doth imply, that Chriſtians may worſhip the very Images. The two maine reaſons he rendreth wherefore the Heathen did adore the very Images, are theſe. <hi>Quia mouebantur, &amp; loque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Imag. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> becauſe they ſeemed to moue and ſpeake: <hi>&amp; quia praedita erant forma humana;</hi> and becauſe they had the members of men: things not vnuſuall amongſt our Aduerſaries.</p>
            <p>I adde, that Chriſtians doe worſhip the very I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and that with diuine Honour. <hi>Wee cenſe them,</hi> ſayth Biſhop <hi>Bonner. Suaues odores, nos etiam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bonner in Praec.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>in ipſa Eccleſia, offerimus Imaginibus:</hi> Wee offer ſweet odours (euen Incenſe) vnto Images in our Church, ſayth their <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> And when God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. de Eccleſ. Triumph. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>p.</hi> 1957.</note> himſelfe would diſcipher moſt deteſtable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, hee deſcribes them thus: <hi>Euery man, had a Cenſer in his hand. Ezech.</hi> 8. 11. And in the <hi>Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Thus à Pontifice in thuribulum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poni:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pontif. Part.</hi> 2. <hi>de benedict. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua Crucis.</hi>
               </note> that the Pope doth ſtand with a Cenſer in his hand, <hi>&amp; mox Crucem incenſari,</hi> and that Incenſe in that Cenſer is employed about the Croſſe.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, <hi>Nabuchodonoſor, in ſignum honoris iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, ei offerri munera odorum, &amp; ſuffituum, id quod nos etiam ſecundùm fidem noſtram Imaginibus facere conſueuimus. Nabuchodonoſor</hi> (ſayth <hi>Vaſquez)</hi> by way of honour, commanded that Odours and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vaſquez. de Adorat. Diſp.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> ſhould be offered vnto <hi>Daniel:</hi> which wee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22564:19"/> alſo, according to our Faith, vſe to performe vnto Images. And (which is yet more conſiderable) the ſame <hi>Vaſquez</hi> in the ſame booke concludeth, that <hi>Hezechiah</hi> did breake the braſen Serpent, <hi>quia illi adolebant Incenſum,</hi> becauſe they burned Incenſe vnto it: and yet he confeſſeth that they do the ſame to their Images in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot tell how to expreſſe it, nor they how to excuſe it. Thinke withall that they ſweare by them, goe a Pilgrimage to them, a Proceſſion with them, and place them in the principall places of their Churches, to bow and creepe vnto them. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, With diuine Honor externall, could more be done, if the naturall Image of God, <hi>Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> himſelfe, did deſcend viſibly to bee adored? I muſt anſwere my ſelfe: but in the phraſe of holy <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (quoted by our holy Biſhop <hi>Iewell) Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo mihi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuell. Artic.</hi> 14. <hi>ſect.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>dicat, Non est Deus; nam pro qua re ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant, Ara teſtatur:</hi> Let them neuer ſay, Wee doe not worſhip Images as God; Let their Incenſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone teſtifie their Adoration. Or rather I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. de Imagin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>pag.</hi> 2081.</note> in <hi>Bellarmines</hi> owne words: <hi>Etiamſi quis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, id ſe facere propter Deum, vel Chriſtum, non propter Imagines: hoc ipſo, quod eas colit diuinis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noribus, conuincitur: eas colere propter ipſas, non propter Deum: quicquid ipſi verbis dicant.</hi> Let the Image-worſhippers proteſt what they pleaſe, that they worſhip God in the Image, and not the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges themſelues: yet ſo long as we ſee their Practice, wee know they worſhip the very Images indeed, although they ſpeake neuer ſo much to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:22564:20"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Audito nomine Eccleſiae, Hoſtis expalluit:</hi> They <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Camp. Rat.</hi> 3.</note> triumph in Tradition: and preſſe vs with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Practice of the Church, which doth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably proue (ſay they) that the worſhipping of Images is lawfull. This Arch-argument is vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by that Arch-apoſtate. Conſider his confident aſſertion, <hi>Conſilio ſui reditus, ſect.</hi> 23. <hi>pag.</hi> 24. <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam porro Chriſtianam, etiam Antiquiſsimam, Totam, ac Vniuerſalem, ſummo conſenſu, abſque vlla oppoſitione, aut contradictione, ſtatuas ac imagines veneratam eſſe, eſt certiſsimum, ac probatiſsimum:</hi> It is, ſaith he, moſt ſure, and moſt certaine, that the whole ancient Church, with one conſent, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any oppoſition, did practiſe the worſhipping of Images. I cannot ſufficiently admire the impudence of this Aſſertion: which aduanceth it ſelſe with a double inſolent iniurie: the firſt, againſt <hi>God;</hi> and the ſecond, againſt the <hi>Church.</hi> Suppoſe his Braua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do to be true: that the whole ancient Church with one conſent did admit Image-adoration. But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe withall (with your eyes ſee) that Gods Law doth interdict it: Is the <hi>Tradition</hi> of the Church a warrant ſufficient, to iuſtifie the breach of Gods owne <hi>inhibition?</hi> the caſe is here cleere: they are <hi>mandata mea,</hi> not <hi>aliena:</hi> the Commandements of <hi>God,</hi> and not of the <hi>Church,</hi> which muſt iudge or iuſtifie vs at the Day of iudgement. Next, as this Aſſertion wrongeth God, by equalling the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the Church to his Commandement: ſo doth it wrong the Church alſo, by a manifeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying of it: that the whole Church did concurre in one conſent to worſhip Images. <hi>Leo Iſaurus,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:22564:20"/> 
               <hi>Conſt. Copronymus, Leo Armenius, Michael Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> and <hi>Theophilus:</hi> all theſe Emperors were <hi>Ico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomachi,</hi> that is, <hi>enemies to Images,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. de Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> Againe, <hi>Serenus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Marcellis, Claudius</hi> of <hi>Turin, Hincmarus</hi> of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and <hi>Agobardus</hi> of <hi>Lions:</hi> all theſe oppoſed Images, as it is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged on all ſides. Finally, the <hi>Conſtantian</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in the Eaſt, and that of <hi>Franckford</hi> in the Weſt, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chemnit. Exam. part.</hi> 4.</note> did definitiuely condemne Images: and the <hi>Libri Carolini</hi> were wrote at the ſame time, on the ſame Theame. Now, when as fiue <hi>Emperors,</hi> foure <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> &amp; two <hi>Councels,</hi> plainly oppoſed themſelues: Bookes were written, Images broken, and millions ſlaughtered in this cauſe of Images: and that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prognoſticon, the Sunne ſeuenteene dayes dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homil.</hi> of <hi>Idol. part.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 36.</note> when the Emperor was murdered, and Images eſtabliſhed by <hi>Irene:</hi> Where now is that <hi>face,</hi> and whence was that <hi>forehead</hi> hewne, which bluſheth not to ſay that it is moſt certaine, that the whole Church did worſhip Images, with one conſent, and without any oppoſition or contradiction?</p>
            <p>Moreouer, how iniuſtly he doth father this ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie on the old Church, let theſe old Fathers te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, euen out of my ſmall reading. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clem. Alexand. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otreptic. pag.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Are they not monſtrous men (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in a monſtrous errour) who proſtrate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before a ſtony Statue, ſaith <hi>Clem. Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> And the ſame Author ſaith in the ſame place, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Men become the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of Statues, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe cuſtome bereaueth them of their ſences. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iu. Martyr Reſp. ad Orth. Resp.</hi> 43.</note> ſaith <hi>Iuſtin Martyr,</hi> We ſhould worſhip no
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:22564:21"/> things, but ſuch as haue life: we can eaſily aſſume: But Images haue no life: &amp; you can conclude with like facilitie: therefore, we ſhould not worſhip Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> condemneth the idolatrie of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt. in pſal.</hi> 134. 15.</note> Heathen, becauſe they worſhipped that which (was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>), A thing without life, and ſence: the true properties of Images worſhipped by Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans at this day. <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſaith on this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, We are forbidden, a double act, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodoret. in Exod. quaſt.</hi> 38.</note> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, both to Worſhip and to Bow: in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of a double obiect, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Idols, but all Similitudes, ſaith hee, are interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to be adored. All thoſe Scriptures which <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> alleageth againſt the Images of Pagans, may <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr. ad Quiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 59. <hi>Lactant. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> as properly be vrged againſt the Images of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. <hi>Lactantius</hi> doth diſpute the caſe (I may ſay with our Aduerſaries) <hi>Quae dementia est aut ea Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere quae Timeant, aut ea Timere quae Finxerunt?</hi> What a folly-frenſie is it either to make that which you doe feare or worſhip, or to worſhip that which you haue made? <hi>Non ipſa inquiunt timemus, ſed eos ad quorum imaginem ſunt ficta:</hi> We are not ſo groſſe (ſay they) as to feare or worſhip the Image: but in the Image, the thing which is repreſented by the Image. <hi>Nempe eos in coelo arbitramini: cur ergo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culos ad coelum non tollitis? Cur ligna &amp; lapides ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatis?</hi> You ſuppoſe then, that thoſe whom you worſhip are in Heauen: Why then doe you not lift vp your eyes to Heauen? Why lookeſt thou on that picture, on that ſtocke or ſtone? Thus <hi>Lactantius</hi> argueth this very Controuerſie: Let our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſtudie how to anſwer him. For my part, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22564:21"/> bee their Aduocate, againſt ſo direct an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arnobius</hi> proſecuteth the ſame Argument, which may be applied with a ſmall inuerſion: <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutite</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arnob. Adu. Gent. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 677.</note> 
               <hi>aliquando caliginem:</hi> At length, ſaith he, Put away the miſt from your eyes. <hi>Simulacra iſta, quae vos in templis omnibus proſtrati adoratis, lapides ſunt, &amp; ligna:</hi> The Images which you worſhip in all your Churches (looke on them) alas, they are but ſtocks and ſtones. <hi>Deos inquitis per ſimulacra vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramur:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 671.</note> It may be you excuſe your ſelues, that it is but veneration, and not to the Image, but through the Image to the Saints. <hi>Quid ſi coli ſe neſciunt dij?</hi> What if thoſe Saints bee not <hi>omniſcious?</hi> What if they doe not ſee your adoration? Are not you then blind idolaters? Saint <hi>Augustines</hi> ſaying is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, though it may be not ſo pat to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as the premiſes. <hi>Et Idola quidem omni ſenſu</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. Ep.</hi> 49. <hi>queſt.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 194</note> 
               <hi>carere, quis dubitet? verum cum his locantur ſedibus, honorabili ſublimitate, vt à precantibus, &amp; immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantibus attenduntur: ipſa ſimilitudine animatorum membrorum, &amp; ſenſuum, quamuis inſenſata, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anima, afficiunt infirmos animos, vt viuere, ac ſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re videantur:</hi> Who is ſo ſtupid, as not to know that an Image hath neither life, nor ſence? yet is it not poſſible, that their place, in the principall part of the Church, the people practiſe to bow before, and to make Prayers and Oblations to them: and their ſhape and very forme of men. Is it not poſſible, that theſe things may ſo affect the weake mindes of the ſilly Vulgar, that they may thinke, that they haue euen life, and ſence alſo?</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:22564:22"/>
            <p> Theſe Fathers haue argued, they ſhall alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude for vs. <hi>Arnobius</hi> concludeth the very point: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arnob. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 673.</note> 
               <hi>Ridetis priſcis temporibus Perſas; Fluuios coluiſſe, Arabas Lapidem, acinacem Scythas, Lignum Carios pro Diana, &amp;c. &amp; abſtinetis à riſu, cum pro Dijs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalibus, ſigilliolis hominum, &amp; formis ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis humanis?</hi> So hee of the old <hi>Romans:</hi> and this I bring home to the doores of the preſent <hi>Romans:</hi> You laugh to heare that the Heathen idolaters did adore, ſome the Riuers, ſome a Sword, others a piece of wood for <hi>Diana:</hi> and Stocks and Stones, for their other Deities.</p>
            <p>And can you abſtaine from laughing, to thinke that your ſelues doe worſhip the Saints in Pictures, and a piece of wood for the Perſon of the Sauiour of the whole World? <hi>Lactantius</hi> his concluſion is very <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lactant. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note> confident, <hi>Non eſt dubium quin nulla religio ſit, vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſimulacrum eſt:</hi> It is certaine, there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whereſoeuer there are any Images worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: Images I ſay; for what elſe is <hi>ſimulacrum?</hi> Let our Aduerſaries diſtinguiſh of this <hi>Cenſure.</hi> And yet Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> doth anticipate their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt.</hi> 49. <hi>Deo gratias.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Diſtinctions. Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illinc excuſant impij ſua ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilega ſacra, &amp; ſimulacra, quod eleganter interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur, quid quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſignificant:</hi> Neither can any I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage-Patron excuſe their Image-Adoration, by varniſhing it ouer with the pretie colours of their nice Diſtinctions.</p>
            <p>Here is enough for this point: but that one of their owne ſaith more, and driueth the Naile to the very head. <hi>Pereſius</hi> deliuereth wordes, which are as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pereſius de Tra. part.</hi> 3. <hi>de imag.</hi>
               </note> it were <hi>Antipodes</hi> to thoſe of <hi>Spalato. Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:22564:22"/> 
               <hi>neque Traditionem Eccleſiae, neque communem ſenſum ſanctorum, neque Concilij generalis determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationem aliquam; neque rationem, qua hoc efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuaderi poteſt, adducunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pereſius.</hi> And <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caſſand. Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio Tit. de Imag.</note> concurreth in the ſame Concluſion, that is: No man (ſay theſe men, our Aduerſaries) can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce either Scripture, or Tradition, or conſent of Fathers, or definition of any generall Councell, or any ſound Reaſon, whereby they can plainly proue the lawfulneſſe of the worſhipping of Images.</p>
            <p>Thus their Cloud of <hi>Traditions</hi> is vaniſhed like the morning deaw before the Sunne: they dimme not our eyes from ſeeing this <hi>Truth</hi> as cleere as the Sunne at noone day. Images are not to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped.</p>
            <p>At the end, when a battaile is defeated, a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Souldier receiuing a mortall wound, when he can doe no more, he doth what he can: in furie he draweth the weapon out of the wound, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it in pieces. So this plaine precept, hauing ſmote this prime point of Controuerſies thorow the loynes: the Idol-champions act their laſt furious part, in breaking this ſecond Commandement into pieces, two wayes; by Incluſion, and Excluſion. Firſt, ſome include this in the firſt, and ſay that it is but a part of that Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt haue no other Gods but me,</hi> with an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in ſtead of this long Commandement, both in their Catechiſmes, and in their Controuerſies alſo. So <hi>Coſterus</hi> alleag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coſter. Ench. cap.</hi> 13.</note> our principall Argument, omitteth the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall part of our Argument, <hi>Non facies tibi ſculptile, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vllam ſimilitudinem; Thou ſhalt not make to</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:22564:23"/> 
               <hi>thy ſelfe any grauen Image, nor any likeneſſe of any thing,</hi> leauing out that thing which is moſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, <hi>Non adorabis ea; Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them.</hi> But this ſhuffling maketh their Cauſe the more ſuſpicious: hee that putteth out the Candle, doth kindle a conceit, that there may be ſome thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, and it is a pretie trick of petie Pilferers, when they haue ſtollen one bagge of Ten, to diuide one of the Nine into Two, to make vp the number. But God be bleſſed, his prouidence hath preuented this ſacriledge. For, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 7. <hi>Thou ſhalt not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet thy neighbours houſe: Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours wife:</hi> but, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 21. it is inuerted, <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours wife: Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours houſe.</hi> The <hi>Tenth</hi> can bee but one Commandement: if the <hi>Second</hi> be none, then are there but nine Commandements, and this is ſhort meaſure for a <hi>Decalogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next is more groſſe: a peremptorie exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this Commandement, auouching it to bee Poſitiue, and proper onely to the <hi>Iewes:</hi> not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and obligatorie to the whole world. This is the refined deuice of <hi>Vaſques:</hi> and this ſeemeth to bee <note place="margin">Vaſques de Adorat.</note> the ſcope of ſubtle <hi>Suarez,</hi> though he carry it more couertly. Said, I ſay, it is by ſome of our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to bee ceremoniall, and therefore not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne vs Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The Heathens had an Hieroglyphick, expreſſed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rainold. de Idol. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 49</note> by fiue figures, a <hi>Child,</hi> an old <hi>Man,</hi> an <hi>Hawke,</hi> a <hi>Fiſh,</hi> and an <hi>Hippopotamus,</hi> or Horſe of <hi>Nilus,</hi> wherein the impreſe was, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>O yee who are comming into the</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:22564:23"/> 
               <hi>world, and yee who are going out of the world, God doth hate impudence.</hi> By the <hi>Child</hi> they vnderſtood <hi>Life,</hi> or Men comming into the world: by the old <hi>Man, Death,</hi> or ſuch as are going out of the world: by the <hi>Hawke</hi> (which is of a moſt quick ſight) the <hi>omniſcient</hi> God: by the <hi>Fiſh</hi> (which is an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the <hi>Egyptians) Hatred:</hi> and by the <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popotamus</hi> (which is ſaid vnnaturally to kil the Sire, and to force the Damme) <hi>Impudence.</hi> I may make bold to make vſe of this phraſe: I ſay therefore, O yee <hi>Romiſts,</hi> from the old <hi>Cardinall</hi> to the young <hi>Nouice:</hi> Know that the <hi>Eagle-eye</hi> of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance will purſue that hated <hi>Wretch</hi> to perdition; who dare ſo to ſmite his <hi>Father, God:</hi> and to offer ſuch violence to his <hi>Mother,</hi> the <hi>Church:</hi> as to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie, and nullifie that <hi>Precept,</hi> which <hi>Hee</hi> hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and <hi>Shee</hi> ſhould keepe.</p>
            <p>Conſider the commination, God will viſite I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage-adorers: the commendation, God calleth it <hi>loue,</hi> if men will not worſhip them: the long plague, <hi>I will viſite the third and fourth generations of them that doe worſhip:</hi> and the longer promiſe, <hi>I will ſhew mercy vnto thouſands,</hi> of them that doe not breake, but <hi>keepe</hi> amongſt the reſt, eſpecially this <hi>Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</hi> The Titles; of himſelfe, <hi>I am a iealous God:</hi> of the Sinne, <hi>Iniquitie,</hi> and the hatred of God, to bow to an Image. Now is all this but <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue?</hi> but <hi>Ceremoniall?</hi> but for a <hi>People?</hi> but for a <hi>Seaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But where as God hath written in this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, as it were in great letters, that hee which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:22564:24"/> runneth may reade them, <hi>Mandatum meum,</hi> My Commandement: for Man to blot this out, and in the ſtead thereof to write <hi>Mandatum nullum,</hi> No Commandement: This is ſomewhat harſh; to ſay no more. Whereas God ſaith here; <hi>I will ſhew mercy vnto thouſands of them that keepe,</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data mea, <hi>my Commandements;</hi> to reply, Lord we will haue thy mercies, and we doe keepe, <hi>Mandata tua,</hi> thy Commandements; onely this long Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is <hi>Mandatum nullum,</hi> no Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: it is ceremoniall, it concerneth not vs. Can we conceiue this without bluſhing?</p>
            <p>Leaue we then the Image-worſhippers to their ſhifts and ſubtilties. For vs, let vs vſe almoſt the words of their <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in this caſe, though in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. <hi>pag.</hi> 2077.</note> another branch thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Dicent fortaſſe praeceptum loquitur de Latria per ſe, &amp; non propter aliud:</hi> Peraduenture they will diſtinguiſh of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. <hi>Nil facit ad rem: hic enim non de ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, ſed de verbis agimus:</hi> Their Diſtinctions are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe; for wee are here to conſider the wordes of the Commandement. <hi>Satis nobis eſt in praecepto ſimpliciter negari, imaginibus deberi la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam:</hi> It is ſufficient for our ſides if the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement doe plainly prohibite the worſhipping of Images. <hi>Nos enim modum loquendi praeceptorum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui debemus:</hi> We are bound (I hope I may ſpeake that of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſpake of the Councels.) We are bound, I ſay, to follow the letter of the Law.</p>
            <p>And the letter of the Law, I am ſure, runneth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22564:24"/> roundly for our cauſe: <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, nor any likeneſſe, of any thing, that is in Heauen aboue, or in the Earth beneath, or in the Water vnder earth. Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, nor worſhip them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus long haue I beene <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and haue ſhewed what they can ſay for Images. Now I muſt bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſhew what wee can ſay againſt Images. A few blowes will bee enough faſtned on a feeble Aduerſarie: I will diſpatch this diſcourſe very ſpeedily. As <hi>Debora</hi> ſang of the Heauens, <hi>Iudges</hi> 5. 20. that the <hi>Starres</hi> therein <hi>in their courſes fought againſt Siſera:</hi> ſo may I ſay of this Precept, that the <hi>Points</hi> herein, <hi>in their courſes fight against Images.</hi> In the <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> the firſt Point is the prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition: <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image,</hi> that is, without authoritie from God. Let all our Image-worſhippers, ſhew any one authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie out of the Scriptures, for the making and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Images, and wee contend no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And as it followeth in the plaine ſyllables of the Expoſition: if their Crucifixes, Roodes, and other Images, be not <hi>ſome likeneſſe, of ſome thing, either in Heauen aboue,</hi> or <hi>in the Earth beneath,</hi> or <hi>in the Water vnder the Earth;</hi> then will wee caſt downe our weapons, and confeſſe them Conquerors.</p>
            <p>For their <hi>Practice:</hi> if it doth not (by their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, Precations, Pilgrimages, Proceſſions, Cenſings, &amp;c.) exhibite that ſuperiour worſhip in the higheſt degree, euen an externall <hi>Latria,</hi> befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:22564:25"/> euen Chriſt himſelfe, if corporally preſent; then may they excuſe.</p>
            <p>But if they doe not performe that <hi>inferiour pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> and doe not <hi>bow to a grauen Image,</hi> then will wee bow to them, and begge forgiueneſſe for our calumnie: but if they doe,—then deeme I it their dutie to bow to God, and craue pardon for their idolatrie.</p>
            <p>The Arguments, drawne from Gods iuſtneſſe and goodneſſe, are rather from Images then againſt Images: and therefore they ſeeme not very perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to this point. Yet it will appeare, that theſe alſo, are not like <hi>Meroz, Iudges</hi> 5. 21. but that they alſo come forth to the helpe of the Lord, to the helpe of the Lord againſt the mightie.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Puniſher,</hi> God: is expreſſed by a dreadfull Title; He is a <hi>jealous God!</hi> Now, when a iealous man will excuſe his wife, who hath communicated her Bed and Body to another, mitigating that Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the manner thereof, and the qualitie of the Perſon: then will our <hi>jealous God</hi> approoue the worſhipping of Images, qualified by quaint Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> is powred on Perſons, who are here ſaid to <hi>hate God;</hi> and ſuch are the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of Images; <hi>effectiuè,</hi> at the leaſt. By it they haue occaſioned the Heathen to <hi>hate</hi> Chriſt, and Chriſtianitie. Images haue beene an infinite ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall to the Turkes, to the Iewes, and to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, as it is auouched by learned <hi>Chemnitius.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exam. part.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Gods <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> both in regard of the Qualitie,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22564:25"/> 
               <hi>Mercy:</hi> and of the Quantitie thereof, <hi>to Thouſands:</hi> is inlarged to ſuch as are ſo qualified as the Text mentioned, who in declining of Images, doe keepe <hi>Mandata mea,</hi> eſchewing this ſinne forbidden in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scripture</hi> (is our <hi>Dauid</hi> againſt the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims)</hi> it bringeth forth an armie of Arguments againſt Images. Of this Armie of allegations, I will draw out (like <hi>Gedeon, Iudges</hi> 7.) onely ſome fewe ſelected Voluntaries; although a multitude might bee preſt forth to this purpoſe. Theſe alſo (as <hi>Dauid</hi> did his mightie men, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.) I will reduce to three Companies. I will oppoſe Images, from the Law, from the Prophets, and from the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Law,</hi> you ſee, the very Letter thereof doth ſmite downe Images in this Commandement: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, wee haue a Caueat, not to make the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, <hi>Dent.</hi> 4. 15. A command not to bow to an Image, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 1. And becauſe they did make an Image, and bow to it, Thouſands dyed for it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 28.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Prophets: Eſay</hi> ſaith, <hi>They that make an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, are all of them vanitie,</hi> 44. 9. <hi>A molten I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage is a Teacher of lyes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Habbakkuk</hi> 3. 18. but of all that is moſt fearfull, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97. 7. <hi>Confounded be all they that worſhip carued Images.</hi> The curſe of God ſtriketh ſomewhat neerer then a <hi>Trent Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema:</hi> and the <hi>Trent</hi> abettors, had neede to take notice of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>New Testament: To change the glorie of God</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:22564:26"/> 
               <hi>into the Image of a man, was</hi> the ſinne of the <hi>Pagans,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 1. 23. And it ſhall bee the propertie of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> that his ſeruants ſhall worſhip <hi>Idols,</hi> or <hi>Images,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn, Reuel.</hi> 9. 20. and therefore that wee ſhould bee neither ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> nor reduced to <hi>Paganiſme:</hi> the Apoſtle ſhutteth vp his Epiſtle with that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticall <hi>Caue,</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. <hi>vlt. Babes take heed of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols;</hi> not onely of <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> but of <hi>Idols,</hi> and the very occaſion thereof.</p>
            <p>Now, I may vſe the phraſe of that Heathen Iudge: <hi>Si hic non ſit teſtimoniorum ſatis, neſcio quid ſit ſatis:</hi> If theſe bee not teſtimonies enough, I know not what is enough. But this I know, that they all giue plaine witneſſe to the plaine wordes of my Text. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image.</hi> Therefore; Image-adoration is moſt abominable.</p>
            <p>Let mee craue your leaue, that I may take my leaue in a word of Exhortation: God knoweth when we ſhall meet here againe together; let not therefore my long <hi>Vale</hi> tire you, though it bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſomewhat ouer-tedious.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, I addreſſe my ſpeech two wayes, to two ſorts of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Catholikes. Some are <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidi,</hi> reſolute in their determinations: others are <hi>molliores,</hi> more moderate in their opinions.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, I ſhould preſume, if I ſhould but hope, to preuaile with them by perſwaſion. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that peremptorie proteſtation of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> in the ſeuenth Synode. <hi>Potiùs om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:22564:26"/> 
               <hi>lupanaria eſſe intranda, quàm intermitten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chemnit. Exam. part.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 63.</note> 
               <hi>adorationem illius Imaginis:</hi> That hee had rather men ſhould enter all the Stewes, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the adoration of that Image.</p>
            <p>And I cannot forget that three Popes, <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorius</hi> the third, <hi>Adrian</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Leo</hi> the third <hi>(Bellarmine</hi> is my Authour) that they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. de Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</note> fell from the Emperours, excommunicated their Perſons, inhibited their Tribute, and thruſt them out of their Dominions: all this, for this one Point, becauſe they oppoſed the worſhipping of Images. I knowe alſo that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie is a lye, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Of all errors: and that there are ſuch, who <hi>beleeue a lye,</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal.</hi> 2. 11. and therefore their <hi>Faith</hi> is faſtned on this <hi>Tradition,</hi> as the <hi>Truth</hi> is on Gods <hi>Word, Matth.</hi> 5. 18. <hi>Heauen and Earth ſhall paſſe, before they will alter one jot, or tittle of their Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore I ſay, I preſume not to perſwade them to an alteration of this point of their Religion: yet I deſpaire not, to intreate them to a mitigation of one affection in their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; that they would not hate vs, becauſe indeed we doe hate their Images. I will ſpeake <hi>Bellarmines</hi> owne wordes. <hi>Eos male agere, quòd</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. de Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 2031.</note> 
               <hi>pro Imaginibus ſuis, Dei occiderent Imagines.</hi> Surely thoſe Catholikes doe not well in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs, who are Gods Images, becauſe wee hate Idols, which are their Images.</p>
            <p>Let them not meruaile that I inſiſt ſo much
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:22564:27"/> on this point, that they hate vs, and that for this point, for Images. Although their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der plot would haue buried our Records, yet our Records cannot burie their powder plot. That telleth vs, that they hate vs; and that they hate vs as for Poperie in generall; ſo for Images in particular.</p>
            <p>Were they not Image-worſhippers, which were thoſe powder Pioners? And was it not a miraculous Image, which ſome afterwardes <note place="margin">Garnets ſtraw.</note> produced to iuſtifie, nay to ſanctifie either the Action, or ſome Actor in that conſpiracie? But bleſſed bee God! that Action was indeed an <hi>Image, Idolum, Scimus idolum in mundo nihil eſſe,</hi> it did nothing in the world to hurt vs. And thoſe Actors were meere <hi>Idola,</hi> like the Heathen Images, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135. 15. <hi>They had eyes, but they ſaw not;</hi> that Flame which they looked for. <hi>They had eares, but they heard not;</hi> that Cracke which they prayed for. <hi>They had</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The ſeuen Sparkes.</note> 
               <hi>mouthes, but they breathed not;</hi> out that threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hauocke to our Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, which they conſpired for. O then, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you eſteeme vs not Chriſtians, yet abate, abate, as yee are men, abate this inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane crueltie. And if that plot had beene perfected, you had doubtleſſe plagued vs, to the third and fourth Generation: but withall I feare, I feare, you had preuented God from ſhewing mercy (toward your ſelues) euen to <hi>Thouſands.</hi> Therefore for our Bodies ſake, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22564:27"/> for your owne Soules ſake: Bleſſed bee our God, for that bleſſed preuention.</p>
            <p>But to thoſe who are diſpoſed more mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I dare vnboſome my Exhortation more boldly. Some <hi>Romiſh</hi> Catholikes, I beare them <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 30. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> record, that they haue zeale, but not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to knowledge: and I know, God will ſhewe mercy to the ignorant; prouided that their ignorance bee not affected, and that they take not pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Let me ſpeake therefore vnto you, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did to <hi>Agrippa: Doe you beleeue the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Scriptures? I know you doe beleeue them.</hi> If you doe! Thinke you: Is not this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Scripture? Are they not the very ſyllables of this Commandement which I haue read to you? yea, let mee preſſe you a little farther. Haue I not laid open all your ſtarting holes? that your beſt Arguments are but Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaues, not able to couer the apparent naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your idolatrie? Let me therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent your conſcience: and in the ſight of your conſcience, and of God himſelfe, let mee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure you to reade ouer this long Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againe and againe, at your beſt leaſure. And then conſider aduiſedly, whether GOD doth not ſeeme to ſpeake to you, as hee did to <hi>Ionah: Doeſt thou well to bee angrie for the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionah</hi> 4. 3.</note> 
               <hi>gourd?</hi> ſo here, doe you well to be angrie for the forbidding of Image-worſhip? But if you ſhould anſwere GOD for your errour, as <hi>Ionah</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.</note>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:22564:28"/> did for his anger; <hi>Wee doe well to worſhip I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, euen vnto death,</hi> that you will die in that Deuotion: Then doe I feare that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth <hi>verſe</hi> of the nintie ſeuen <hi>Pſalme</hi> will be the Epitaph on your Graue-ſtone: <hi>Confounded are all they which worſhip carued Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beloued, I hope for, and pray for better things, for many of you: euen ſuch things, as may <hi>accompanie ſaluation.</hi> To which end, conſider this plaine <hi>Commandement! Not any likeneſſe, of any thing,</hi> in any place. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider alſo the <hi>Argument.</hi> The <hi>Puniſher, a iealous God,</hi> whome yee cannot blinde with your blanch'd excuſes. The <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> he will <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite</hi> the <hi>ſinnes of the Fathers on the Children, to the third and fourth generation,</hi> that is, if you perſiſt, Gods viſitations and plagues may bee powred on your owne <hi>Perſons,</hi> yea and on your <hi>childrens children,</hi> and your owne eyes ſhall behold them.</p>
            <p>But if you <hi>conuert</hi> (Chriſt moue your hearts to ſuch a happy conuerſion) then <hi>mercies</hi> ſhall bee multiplyed vpon you in <hi>Thouſands:</hi> you ſhall bee made the inſtruments to <hi>ſaue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands</hi> of ſoules, of ſuch as ſhall iſſue from your owne bodies.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you therefore, for Gods <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and for Gods <hi>Mercies,</hi> for Gods ſake, for your owne ſake, for your childrens ſake, yea for your childrens childrens ſake, for the ſake of a thouſand Soules yet vnborne: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22564:28"/> you Brethren, I beſeech you, conſider what I ſay; and God almightie giue you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in all things.</p>
            <p>But be it ſo, that in Gods ſecret <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> or in his ſacred <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> our Aduerſaries doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme theſe poore wordes of mine, to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but <hi>Wordes,</hi> but <hi>Winde,</hi> but <hi>Water</hi> ſpilt vpon the ground, not worth the taking vp: yet you, who are <hi>Friends, Brethren,</hi> and <hi>Fellow-members,</hi> bee yee <hi>Gedeons fleece,</hi> attract this deaw of Heauen, more then the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes (that is in their ſence) more then all the world beſides. A motiue: Conſider the <hi>Controuerſie</hi> betwixt vs. It is not (as <hi>Bellarmines</hi> phraſe is) <hi>de ſtillicidijs,</hi> concerning that <hi>Eaues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dropping, Houſe ranſacking, Soule-ſifting, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome-exenterating, Auricular Confeſsion;</hi> though that bee a ſtrange intruding myſticall policie. It is not <hi>de vno apice,</hi> of one Point, that full Point, where the Papiſts would pitch their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, the <hi>Papacie,</hi> the <hi>Primacie;</hi> though that be an inſolent inſulting proud <hi>Tyrannie.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it onely an <hi>hereſie;</hi> although the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping euen of Chriſts <hi>Image,</hi> was eſteemed an <hi>hereſie,</hi> by <hi>Irenaeus, Epiphanius, Auguſtine,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>pag.</hi> 2081.</note> and <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe doth te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie. But it is <hi>Idolatrie: Idolatrie,</hi> at the very name whereof, <hi>Heauen</hi> doth lament, <hi>Hell</hi> tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, and the <hi>Earth</hi> cannot but quake and tremble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> of which <hi>Perinottus</hi> proteſted, that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22564:29"/> the Emperour could ſuffer any reproach of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, <note place="margin">Melchior. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. in vita Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</note> abuſes: but of Idolatrie, hee was impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, as of a thing inſufferable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> for which <hi>Claudius</hi> and <hi>Nicoſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. de Imag. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> expert Statuaries, were put to death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not make ſuch Statues; chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rather to die, then to giue the occaſion of Idolatrie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> of which <hi>Spalato</hi> ſpeaketh: that <hi>Idolatrie</hi> is worſe then moſt <hi>Hereſie:</hi> Idolaters <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſilio ſui Reditus, ſect.</hi> 2.</note> to bee ſeparated from by all men. <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> is the crime from which God doth command you, and I perſwade you.</p>
            <p>Now, that worſhipping of Images is Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, I neede not tell you; <hi>ex ore infantium,</hi> when you catechiſe your children, your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren will catechiſe you, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, &amp;c.</hi> But nowe you know it, your care muſt be to ſhunne it. For<hi>—the Lord is a iealous God,</hi> and will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce that <hi>Soule,</hi> which ſhall ſinne by <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> by ſpirituall <hi>Adulterie,</hi> and Hee will <hi>viſite—</hi>ſend out a plague. It is <hi>Carions</hi> opinion, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Carion. Chron. lib.</hi> 2.</note> the <hi>Turkes</hi> haue ouer-run ſo much of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> for this one ſinne of Idolatrie. How ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer our <hi>Securitie</hi> may ſuppoſe the <hi>Turks</hi> long armes too ſhort to reach vs ſo farre off: Yet (if wee become Idolaters) may <hi>Hee,</hi> or ſome ſuch as <hi>Hee,</hi> by Gods permiſſion, <hi>viſite vs—</hi>But the Lord bleſſe vs from ſuch a <hi>viſitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this <hi>Viſitation</hi> may bee deriued to the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:22564:29"/> 
               <hi>third and fourth generation:</hi> if you worſhip I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, you may ſee Gods plagues on the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in this world: and in the world to come you may heare your childrens children, crie out in that phraſe of Saint <hi>Cyprian; Heu paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſenſimus parricidas:</hi> alas, our Parents haue damned vs, by their exemplarie Idolatrie.</p>
            <p>But I paſſe theſe puniſhments, perſwading my ſelfe that I ſhall perſwade you from <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</hi> You being <hi>Sonnes</hi> or <hi>Seruants,</hi> not <hi>Slaues;</hi> to be led with gentleneſſe, and not to bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with whipping: Beware then of <hi>Images,</hi> becauſe God will bequeath <hi>mercy vnto Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands,</hi> and <hi>Thouſands of mercies vnto you,</hi> if you doe beware.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Meanes</hi> alſo God ſetteth before you; <hi>Amor mei,</hi> and <hi>Mandata mea.</hi> If you haue the <hi>loue of God</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> your <hi>Hearts,</hi> and the <hi>Law of God</hi> in your <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Image-Idolatrie</hi> will finde you impregnable. <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> in the later Ages, may perhaps ſtagger the <hi>Ignorant:</hi> but <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data mea,</hi> Gods Law doth obſcure Mans Law, as the Sunne doth the ſmalleſt Candle! Reade the Scriptures, and it is impoſſible to bee inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to <hi>Idolatrie.</hi> For the other branch: The loue of <hi>Trafficke</hi> may preuaile with <hi>Merchants;</hi> the loue of <hi>Noueltie</hi> with <hi>Trauellers;</hi> the loue of <hi>Profit</hi> with <hi>Trades-men;</hi> the loue of <hi>Pleaſure</hi> with <hi>Gallants;</hi> and the loue of <hi>Preferment</hi> with the <hi>Ambitious.</hi> Moreouer, men may bee allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Idolatrie</hi> by the loue of <hi>Friends,</hi> by the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:22564:30"/> loue of <hi>Parents,</hi> by the loue of <hi>Children,</hi> by the loue of a <hi>Wife,</hi> or by the loue of a <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi> O but let theſe petie <hi>Streames</hi> fall into this mayne <hi>Ocean.</hi> Let this <hi>Loue of God,</hi> ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp all theſe <hi>Loues</hi> of <hi>Men.</hi> And the force of this <hi>Loue</hi> conſtrayneth mee, at the very thought of <hi>Images,</hi> to <hi>Bow</hi> my <hi>knees</hi> to <hi>You,</hi> that <hi>You</hi> would neuer <hi>bow your knees</hi> to <hi>Them.</hi> And <hi>God</hi> himſelfe bow all your <hi>Hearts</hi> to <hi>Him,</hi> that you may <hi>Neuer</hi> bow to any <hi>Images. Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:22564:30"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
